Guide to the John Christopher Schwab Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Christopher Schwab family papers
1767-1925
MS 434
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10.25
(21 boxes)
The papers include correspondence, diaries, notebooks, writings, wills, scrapbooks, albums, genealogical records and memorabilia of several generations of the Schwab family. Principal figures are Gustav Friedrich Schwab; his wife, Eliza Catherine Von Post Schwab; and their son, John Christopher Schwab. The papers of Gustav Friedrich Schwab include business correspondence during his presidency of the firm of Oelrichs & Co. in New York and travel diaries (1843-1846). An additional diary (1883) records his travels during the opening excursion of the Northern Pacific Railroad. The papers of his wife contain an autograph album and diaries (1847-1877). The papers also include material of the German poet Gustav Benjamin Schwab, who was the grandfather of John C. Schwab. The papers of John C. Schwab include his student notebooks both in the United States and in Germany, with half of one notebook (1887-1888) devoted to the lectures of the historian Heinrich von Treitschke.
Schwab, John Christopher, 1865-1916
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were donated by Norman Schwab, 1943.
Arrangement
Aranged in two series: I. Correspondence and Papers, 1775-1915. II. Volumes and Miscellanea, 1767-1925.
Scope and Contents
The John C. Schwab Family Papers consist of correspondence, papers, albums, notebooks, diaries, scrapbooks and other material documenting the professional career and personal life of John C. Schwab and his family. The papers are arranged in twenty-one boxes and total ten and one-quarter (10.25) linear feet. Span dates for the material are 1767-1925, and bulk dates range from 1880-1890. The papers were donated to Yale University by Norman Schwab in 1943.
The papers are arranted in two series: I. CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS, 1755-1915; II. VOLUMES AND MISCELLANEA, 1767-1925.
SERIES I contains correspondence between family members in Germany and the United States. These letters include exchanges between Gustav Friedrich Schwab, his wife Eliza Catherine Von Post Schwab, and their son John Christopher Schwab. A portion of this correspondence relates to Gustav Friedrich Schwab's presidency of the New York firm of Oelrichs and Company.
SERIES II contains the personal papers and manuscripts of several family members. Albums, diaries, and manuscripts of Gustav Friedrich Schwab include a diary of his travels and an essay on the opening excursion of the Northern Pacific Railroad (1883). A small quantity of material relating to the poet Gustav Benjamin Schwab is also included in this series. Materials relating to John Christopher Schwab include personal diaries, student notebooks, scrapbooks, and photograph albums.
Biographical / Historical
JOHN CHRISTOPHER SCHWAB, 1865-1916; B.A. 1886
Born April 1,1865, in New York City
Died January 12, 1916, in New Haven, Conn.
John Christopher Schwab, son of Gustav Schwab, of the firm of Oelrichs & Company, was born April 1, 1865, in New York City, being named for his great-grandfather, a privy counsellor of Stuttgart, Germany. His paternal grandparents were Gustav Schwab, a German poet of note, and Sophie (Gmelin) Schwab. His mother was Catherine Elizabeth, daughter of Laurence Henry and Henrietta Margaretta (Meier) Von Post. Through her, he was descended from Heinrich Melchior Mühlenberg, the chief founder of the Lutheran Church in America.
He was fitted for Yale under private tutors and at Gibbons' and Beach's School in New York City. He received several prizes in English and Latin composition, High Oration appointments, and was a member of Phi Beta Kappa in college. As a Sophomore, he sang on his Class Glee Club, and the next year he was a member of the Second Glee Club. He was an editor of the Courant in his Senior year.
He remained at Yale for a year of post-graduate study in political economy after taking the degree of BA, in 1886, and during this period was also an instructor in German at the Hopkins Grammar School. In July, 1887, he went to Europe, and after spending the summer in travel, entered the University of Berlin. His studies for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy were completed at the University of Göttingen in 1889, and he then returned to the United States and spent some time in historical research in the libraries of New York City. He had received an M.A. in course at Yale in 1888. In the fall of 1890, he took up his work as lecturer in political economy at the University, being made an instructor in that department in the following year. He was promoted to an assistant professorship in 1893, and to a full professorship five years afterwards.
In 1905, after seven years of service in that capacity, Professor Schwab was chosen University librarian, and the remainder of his life was devoted to the upbuilding of the Library. A member of the University Council since his appointment as librarian, he had served for some years on the Council's Committee on Publications, in connection with the work of the University Press. In 1901, he supervised the arrangements for the Yale Bicentennial as chairman of the committee in charge of the celebration. He was a frequent contributor to historical journals and magazines, and at one time was editor of the Yale Review. "The Finances of the Confederate States of America," published by Professor Schwab in 1901, is considered a valuable addition in the field of economic history. He was elected Secretary of the Yale Class of 1886 in 1905, and held that office until his death. To the work of civic betterment in New Haven, professor Schwab gave much of his attention, and at the time of his death he was serving as secretary and treasurer of the social settlement known as Lowell House. He was also president of the Model Housing Association of New Haven. He was on the board of trustees of the New Haven Public Library and a member of St. Paul's Protestant Episcopal Church, of whose Sunday school he was at one time superintendent, and for several years served in Company F, Second Regiment, Connecticut National Guard. He was a trustee of Mount Holyoke College, and in 1913 was on the committee which arranged the pageant held in celebration of the seventy-fifth anniversary of its founding. He was a member of the American and British Economic associations, the Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Library Association, and of the Century Club of New York. In 1911, he received from Mühlenberg College the honorary degree of LL.D.
Professor Schwab's death occurred unexpectedly at his home in New Haven, January 12, 1916, after a brief illness from pneumonia. He was buried in Grove Street Cemetery in that city.
On October 5, 1893, he was married in New Haven to Edith Aurelia, daughter of Samuel Sparks Fisher, upon whom Yale conferred an honorary degree in 1851, and Aurelia Safford (Crossette) Fisher. She survives him with their two children: Katharine Fisher, a student at Vassar, and Norman Von Post. He leaves also two brothers and three sisters, one of the latter being the widow of Henry Charles White (B.A 1881, LL.B. 1883, M.L. 1884). Another brother, Laurence Henry, graduated from the College in 1878. Gustav Schwab (B.A. 1902) and Laurence Von Post Schwab (B.A. 1913) are nephews.
(Taken from the Yale Obituary Record .)
Americans -- Germany; Business; Emigration and immigration; Families; Germans -- United States; Railroads -- United States; Europe; Germany; New York (State); Autographs; Wills; Diaries; Businessmen; Educators; Adami, Anton-Filippo, -1770; Cohn, Gustav, 1840-1919; Drollinger, Gustav Friedrich; Dwight, Timothy, 1828-1916; Freylinghausen, Gottlieb Anastasius, 1719-1785; Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1856-1930; Kunze, John C. (John Christopher), 1744-1807; Meier, Caspar; Muhlenberg, Frederick Augustus Conrad, 1750-1801; Oelrichs, Hermann, 1850-1906; Punnett, Mary Kunigunde Meier, b.1816; Rösing, Johannes; Schleiden, R. (Rudolf), 1815-1895; Schwab, Benjamin William, 1867-1899; Schwab, Edith Aurelia Fisher, 1862-1922; Schwab, Eliza Catherine von Post, 1829-1904; Schwab, Gustav, 1792-1850; Schwab, Gustav Friedrich, 1822-1888; Schwab, John Christopher, 1865-1916; Schwab, Sophie Caroline, 1795-1865; Treitschke, Heinrich von, 1834-1896; Von Post, Henry Gerhard, 1825-1855; Von Post, Herman Caspar, 1828-1913; Von Post, Simon Hermann, 1798-1868; Weiser, Conrad, 1696-1760; Koontz family; Myers family; Schwab family; Von Post family; Northern Pacific Railway Company; Oelrichs & Company (New York); Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Library
- CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS, 1755-1915; Series I; 2.0 linear feet (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in chronological order.
  - 1755 July - 1856 March (Box 1, Folder 1-33)
  - 1857 March - 1879 May (Box 2, Folder 34-68)
  - 1879 June - 1886 April (Box 3, Folder 69-103)
  - 1886 May - 1902 February (Box 4, Folder 104-145)
  - 1902 March - 1915 Oct, Misc. and undated (Box 5, Folder 146-154)
- VOLUMES AND MISCELLANEA, 1767-1925; Series II; 8.25 linear feet (16 boxes)
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by individual name. Oversize materials are grouped separately in the last four boxes, also in alphabetical order.
  - Jäger, Charlotte (Schwab)
    - Albums presented to Gustav Friedrich and Eliza Catherine (Von Post) Schwab
      - Family history, quotations, silhouettes, and illustrations, 1850 (Box 6, Folder 155)
      - Poems and silhouettes, 1857 (Box 6, Folder 156)
  - Jäger, Georg
    - Congratulatory volume on the fiftieth anniversary of his becoming a doctor, 1858 (Box 6, Folder 157)
  - Kunze, Elizabeth
    - Notebook of music and poetry, 1788, 1806, undated (Box 6, Folder 158)
  - Kunze, John Christopher
    - Diary, 1767 (Box 6, Folder 159)
    - Notebook, "Antilethiium", 1793-1807 (Box 6, Folder 159)
    - Notebook, "Bemerkungen über die Psalmen Davids", undated (Box 6, Folder 159)
  - Meier, Caspar
    - Album of poems and watercolors prepared for his return to New York, 1822 (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - Autograph album, 1793-1805 (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - Notebooks of poems, 1794, undated (Box 6, Folder 161)
  - Meier, Henrietta M.
    - Album and commonplace book of poems, 1824-1828 (Box 7, Folder 162)
  - Von Post, Herman Caspar
    - Diaries
      - Travel in Europe, 1862 (Box 7, Folder 163)
      - Miscellaneous, 1892-1913 (Box 7, Folder 163-164)
    - Memorandum book, with accounts, addresses, estate records, and family history, 1893-1913 (Box 7, Folder 165)
    - Sketchbook, 1884-1889 (Box 7, Folder 165)
    - Will (printed copy), 1912 (Box 7, Folder 165)
  - Von Post, Jane S. (Whitlock)
    - Account book, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 166)
  - Von Post, Lawrenz H.
    - Autograph album, 1822 (Box 7, Folder 166)
  - Von Post, Simon Hermann (1764-1813)
    - Account book, 1800-1819 (Box 7, Folder 167)
  - Von Post, Simon Hermann (1798-1868)
    - Diaries, 1823-1828, 1838-1841 (Box 7, Folder 168-169)
  - Schwab, Benjamin William
    - Scrapbook of Yale memorabilia, 1884-1886 (Box 8, Folder 170)
  - Schwab, Edith Aurelia (Fisher)
    - Sketchbooks, 1880-1891 (Box 8, Folder 171)
  - Schwab, Eliza Catherine (Von Post)
    - Album of poems, 1847-1850 (Box 8, Folder 172)
    - Diaries, 1847, 1850, 1877-1878 (Box 8, Folder 173)
    - Notebook on her children's illnesses, 1852-1882 (Box 8, Folder 173)
  - Schwab, Gustav Benjamin
    - Printed poem and address on the marriage of Georg and Charlotte (Schwab) Jäger, 1819 (Box 8, Folder 174)
  - Schwab, Gustav Friedrich
    - Album of poems, illustrations, and memorabilia, 1835-1848 (Box 8, Folder 175)
    - Autograph album, 1838-1844 (Box 9, Folder 176)
    - Diary of travel in Europe and America, 1843-1846 (Box 9, Folder 176)
    - German Society of the City of New York: memorial resolutions, 1888 (Box 9, Folder 177)
    - Manuscript, "The Opening Excursion over the Northern Pacific Railroad in September 1883" (copies in English and German) (Box 9, Folder 178-179)
    - Muscoota Boat Club: minute book, 1874-1878 (Box 9, Folder 180)
  - Schwab, John Christopher
    - Diaries
      - "Journal of the Family Schwab...", 1880-1881 (Box 9, Folder 181)
      - Miscellaneous, 1882-1893 (Box 9, Folder 181-182)
    - Guest register of JCS and Edith Aurelia (Fisher) Schwab, with autographs and memorabilia, 1893-1917 (Box 10, Folder 183)
    - Manuscript, "Six Weeks in the Alps," with photographs, 1888 (Box 10, Folder 184)
    - Memorabilia, "Relics of Franco-Prussian War", 1870 (Box 10, Folder 185)
    - Notebooks
      - Lectures for his Yale College course, "Public Finance", 1891-1892 (Box 10, Folder 186)
      - "Memorandum for Mr. Schwab's house in Fordham", undated (Box 10, Folder 187)
      - "Statistics of Yale College Graduates," 1849-1903, 1899-1903 (Box 10, Folder 188)
    - Notes for an economic study of American colonial history, undated (Box 11, Folder 189-191)
    - Photograph album of family photographs, undated (Box 11, Folder 192)
    - Photographs and illustrations of family and Fort Number Eight, Circa1869-1914, undated (Box 11, Folder 193)
    - The Revolutionary History of Fort Number Eight
      - Printed copy, with annotations, map, and clippings, 1861, 1897-1900 (Box 12, Folder 194)
      - Printed copy, with MS account of the dedication of a memorial stone, 1897 (Box 12, Folder 195)
      - Sketches and watercolor by JCS and Lucy Sophia (Schwab) White, 1896, undated (Box 12, Folder 196)
    - Scrapbooks
      - Personal and Yale memorabilia, 1882-1887 (Box 13, Folder 197-198)
      - Personal memorabilia
        - 1887-1898 (Box 14, Folder 199)
        - 1898-1904 (Box 15, Folder 200)
    - Student notebooks
      - University of Berlin, University of Göttingen
        - Treitschke, Heinrich von. (Berlin). "Politik", 1887-1888 (Box 15, Folder 201)
        - Schmoller, Gustav von. (Berlin). "Praktische National Ökonomie", 1887-1888 (Box 15, Folder 201)
        - Knoke, K. (Göttingen). "Pädagogik", 1888 (Box 15, Folder 202)
        - Lange, Konrad von. (Göttingen). "Allgemeine Kunstgeschichte", 1888-1889 (Box 15, Folder 202)
        - Weizsäcker, Julius. (Berlin). "Allgemeine Verfassungsgeschichte", 1887-1888 (Box 15, Folder 202)
        - Cohn, Gustav. (Göttingen).
          - Theoretische Nationalökonomie, 1888-1889 (Box 15, Folder 203)
          - Praktische National Ökonomie, 1888 (Box 15, Folder 203)
          - "Finanzwissenschaft", 1888-1889 (Box 15, Folder 203)
        - Lexis, Wilhelm. (Göttingen).
          - Praktische National-Ökonomie, 1888-1889 (Box 15, Folder 203)
          - "Baukwesen", 1888-1889 (Box 15, Folder 203)
          - "Geld & Munzwesen", 1889 (Box 15, Folder 203)
          - "Moralstatistik", 1888-1889 (Box 15, Folder 203)
        - Baumann, Julius. (Göttingen).
          - "Geschichte der neueren Philosophie", 1888-1889 (Box 16, Folder 204)
          - "Logik", 1888-1889 (Box 16, Folder 204)
          - "Erkenntnisstheorie und Metaphysik", 1889 (Box 16, Folder 204)
        - Müller, Gottfried Elias. (Göttingen). "Biophysik", 1889 (Box 16, Folder 204)
      - Yale College
        - Hadley, Arthur Twining.
          - "Railroad Administration", 1886 (Box 16, Folder 205)
          - "Industrial Legislation", 1887 (Box 16, Folder 205)
        - Farnam, Henry Walcott. "Public Finance", 1886-1887 (Box 16, Folder 205)
        - Bourne, Edward Gaylord. "Medieval Industry", 1886-1887 (Box 16, Folder 205)
  - Yale University
    - Committee in charge of the inauguration of President A.T. Hadley: correspondence and papers, 1899 (Box 16, Folder 206-207)
    - Russell Trust Association: photographs from JCS's Skull and Bones album, with autographs, 1886 (Box 16, Folder 208)
  - Schwab, Katharine Fisher
    - Sketchbook, 1910-1914 (Box 17, Folder 209)
  - Schwab family
    - Genealogical notes on various ancestors, undated (Box 17, Folder 210)
  - White, Lucy Sophia (Schwab)
    - Album of pressed flowers, with watercolors and a sketch, 1877-1882 (Box 17, Folder 211)
    - Fort Number Eight: The Home of Gustav and Eliza Schwab (printed copy), 1925 (Box 17, Folder 212)
  - Unidentified
    - Manuscript volume of poems, [1813?] - 1856 (Box 17, Folder 213)
    - Pencil sketch, undated (Box 17, Folder 214)
    - Watercolor, "Bebenhausen", 1877 (Box 17, Folder 214)
  - Oversize
    - Kunze, Henry C. (Box 18, Folder 215)
      - Estate records, 1808-1810 (Box 18, Folder 215)
    - Kunze, John Christopher
      - Petition from members of the German Lutheran Church, New York City, 1806 (Box 18, Folder 215)
      - Photograph of portrait, undated (Box 18, Folder 215)
    - Meier, Caspar
      - Deed for cemetery lot at Reformed Protestant Dutch Church, Harsenville, N.Y., 1826 (Box 18, Folder 216)
      - Will and estate records, 1832, 1839, 1870 (Box 18, Folder 216)
    - Von Post, Herman Caspar
      - Sketchbooks
        - 1848-1867 (Box 18, Folder 217)
        - 1883-1885 (Box 19, Folder 218)
    - Von Post, Lawrenz H.
      - Will, 1840 (Box 19, Folder 219)
    - Schwab, Gustav Friedrich
      - Certificate of citizenship, 1850 (Box 20, Folder 220)
      - Estate records, 1904 (Box 20, Folder 220)
      - Marriage certificate, 1850 (Box 20, Folder 220)
      - Memorial resolutions, 1888 (Box 20, Folder 220)
      - Passports, 1850, 1855 (Box 20, Folder 220)
    - Schwab, John Christopher
      - Manuscript program, "Twelfth Night Procession," Fordham Heights, undated (Box 20, Folder 221)
      - Membership certificates: Massachusetts Historical Society, Society of Colonial Wars, 1902, 1911 (Box 20, Folder 221)
      - Passport, 1887 (Box 20, Folder 221)
      - Scrapbook of family papers and miscellanea, Circa1860-1914 (Box 20, Folder 222)
    - Schwab, Norman Von Post
      - Scrapbook of Taft School autographs, photographs, and memorabilia, 1918-1921 (Box 21, Folder 223)
    - Schwab family
      - Printed matter, mostly biographical, with 2 photographs, 1818-1915 (Box 21, Folder 224)